Guide to the Charles H. Mason Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Charles H. Mason Correspondence
1855-1858
WA MSS 332
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
34
(77 pages)
Mason, Charles H., 1830-1859
Charles H. Mason, 1830-1859
Charles H. Mason was appointed at the age of twenty-three the first secretary of Washington Territory, and served under Governors Stevens and McMullin until his death in 1859. He served as acting governor while Stevens was in the Indian country and after McMullin returned to the East in 1858 until Governor Gholson arrived in 1859.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of thirty-four letters, seventy-seven pages in all, written to and by Charles H. Mason. The majority of the letters relate to the beginnings of Indian hostilities in 1855. Other letters concern Fayette McMullin's attack on Mason's character in 1858.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Washington Territory -- Politics and government; Indians of North America -- Washington (State); Pacific Coast Indians, Wars with, 1847-1865; Politicians -- Washington (State); Curry, Geo. L. (George Law), 1820-1878; Gibbs, George, 1815-1873; McMullin, Fayette, 1805-1880; Mason, Charles H., 1830-1859
- Papers, WA MSS 332
  Scope and Contents
  The following are included in the collection:
  MASON, CHARLES H. Letter to G. Blanchet. December 14, 1855. Signed copy. 1 p.
  MASON, CHARLES H. Letter to Lewis Cass, Secretary of State. June 21, 1858. Signed copy. 10 pp.
  MASON, CHARLES H. Letter to Governor Curry. October 20, 1855. Signed copy. 3 pp.
  MASON, CHARLES H. Three letters to James Douglas. November 10-23, 1855. Signed copies. 5 pp.
  MASON, CHARLES H. Six letters to George Gibbs. September 14 [1855]-January 30,1856. 15 pp.
  MASON, CHARLES H. Letter to Father Ricard. December 4, 1855. Copy. 1 p.
  MASON, CHARLES H. Two letters to General Wool. August 30, October 20, 1855. Copies. 3 pp.
  BLANCHET, GEORGES. Letter to Governor Mason. December 7, 1855, and a copy by Blanchet of the "Commission officielle donnée au P. Pandosy pour être transmise aux soldats." 4 pp.
  CROSBIE, HENRY R. Letter to Acting Governor Mason, resigning as aide to the Governor. November 1, 1855. 1 p.
  CURRY, GEORGE LAW, Governor of Oregon Territory. Three letters to Acting Governor Mason. April 1, 1854-October 25, 1855. Signature only of the second and third in his hand. 7 pp. The letter of October 22, 1855 is endorsed in Elwood Evans' hand: "Advising as to movements &c. of the Oregon Mounted Volunteers."
  GIBBS, GEORGE. Letter to Governor Mason. November 14, 1855. 7 pp.
  MCMULLIN, FAYETTE. Letter about Mason to Lewis Cass, Secretary of State. April 16, 1858. Copy. With a brief note in Evans' hand. 3 pp.
  MCMULLIN, FAYETTE. Letter to U. E. Hicks. April 27,1858. Copy. 1 p.
  MCMULLIN, FAYETTE. Letter to W. W. Miller. April 29, 1858. Copy. 1 p.
  MCMULLIN, FAYETTE. Two letters to R. M. Walker. April 3, 29, 1858. 2 pp.
  OLYMPIA, W. T. CITIZENS. Petition to R. M. Walker, Acting Secretary of the Territory of Washington, for the use of the Capitol for musical concerts and a ball, dated, Olympia, April 26, 1858, and signed by 31 citizens of Olympia. 1 p.
  RAINS, GABRIEL JONES. Letter to Acting Governor Mason. October 9, 1855. Signature only. 2 pp.
  RICARD, PASCAL. Three letters to Acting Governor Mason. October 12-December 1, 1855. 7 pp. With English translations in an unidentified hand; and a copy of Mason's letter to Ricard, December 4, 1855. 1 p.
  TOLMIE, WILLIAM FRASER. Letter to C. H. Mason. October 23, 1855. 2 pp.
  WALKER, RUDOLPH M. Letter to Fayette McMullin, Governor of Washington Territory. April 29, 1858. Copy. 1 p.
  General
  Governor Curry's letter of October 22, 1855, is printed in Evans, History of the Pacific Northwest [1889], I, 551-552; Mason's letters to Douglas, November 23, 1855 and Wool, October 20, 1855, and Rains to Mason, October 9, 1855, are printed in Message of the Governor of Washington Territory [I. I. Stevens], Olympia, 1857, pp. 103, 130, 160. Mason's letter to Douglas, November 23, 1855, is also printed in C. B. Bagley, "Attitude of the Hudson's Bay Company during the Indian War of 1855-1856," Washington Historical Quarterly, 1917, VIII, 299— 300. An extract from Ricard's letter of De-cember 1, 1855, is quoted in English by Denys Nelson in "Yakima Days," idem, 1928, XIX, 128.
  - Correspondence with Georges Blanchet, December 7-14, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence with Governor George Law Curry., April 1, 1854-October 25, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Signed copies of three letters to James Douglas, Governor of Vancouver Island., November 10-23, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence with George Gibbs., September 14, 1855-January 30,1856 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Copies of two letters to General James E. Wool., August 30, October 20, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter from Henry R. Crosbie, resigning as aide to the Governor., November 1, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters concerning the dispute between Mason and Fayette McMullin., April 3-29, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Petition to R.M. Walker, Acting Secretary of the Territory of Washington, from the citizens of Olympia, for the use of the Capitol for musical concerts and a ball., April 26, 1858 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letter to Mason from Gabriel Jones Rains., October 9, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Letters to Mason from Pascal Ricard. With English translations in an unidentified hand; and a copy of Mason's letter to Ricard., October 12-December 4, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letter to Mason from William Fraser Tolmie., October 23, 1855 (Box 1, Folder 11)